And then, let's go ahead and go on to some of the popular things that we use inside of you
is we have computer properties.
And so this is one of my favorite properties of you because what you're ultimately doing
is you're creating an ability to easily cache reactive data that updates automatically
based on another piece of reactive data.
So this is particularly useful when it comes to animations and data tracking and that kind of
stuff because you can do some really incredible things and you don't have to worry about any
of the caching footgun that you might typically have to deal with.
And so in this case, for example, we have this filtered restaurant list, right?
And once again, when people write a method or a computer property, they can find whatever they want.
But it's useful to actually be explicit regarding what it's returning.
So all we need to do here if we want is we can say we're expecting a restaurant and a
array of restaurants. That's what we're expecting.
And so that way if someone comes in and so let's say this side to like,
so not this return statement, this return statement will always return an array of restaurants.
So let's go ahead and botch this real quick and return 1, 2, 3.
You'll see here, hey, wait a second, this return is not right.
And so honestly, if you think about it, what we're doing here with TypeScript is kind of similar
to what you would expect on a word processing like word processor.
Where if the dictionary catches them steak, you kind of wanted to let you know about it.
You don't want to wait till you've printed it and shipped it off to your professor for
grading and be like, Whoops, I have the type of there.
Right, this is one of the things that I think TypeScript does really well.
And as you can see, we're really just progressively sprinkling on some dot what is ultimately
documentation that is then converted into helpful tooltips to make our coding lives easier.
So there you go. We have a list of restaurants from that list.
Now, okay, and what about this? Number of restaurants. Well, as you can see here,
number of restaurants has actually been, this is where what in TypeScript they call type
inference, which is basically it's inferring or assuming what the type will be based on how
the code's written. So in this case, we're using enough vanilla JavaScript here to basically
for TypeScript to recognize that this is probably going to be a number. And in this case,
it's totally right. And so you actually don't need to define it anymore. Because TypeScript
does try to do a lot of the heavy lifting whenever possible. But in case you do want to be explicit,
once again, let's just do that for practice sake. We can just say, okay, we do expect a
number when that comes back. But once again, some people do consider this code clutter. Again,
I leave that to you and your team to decide. But this is also just perfectly valid. It's already
typed. So that in the event, we try to do something funky like this. Actually, this would work,
because I think it's going to, it'll just do some funky things. Because now, if you're always doing
on the inference part, you'll see that you can still mess it up. So when you have things that
a little bit more contingent on what the outcome is, I do actually prefer to be just a little
bit more explicit. And so if we look though, this signature method is actually very similar to
data, because basically you have a function and you're basically after the colon, what you're returning.
So once again, just a show, we have our data here, what we're returning after the parameters,
computed properties, same thing. Okay, so now that we've seen that, very similar, we're going to look
at methods. And so this is where the functions that we're going to use within side of our view components.
And so inside of here, let's start with what we already know, which is what we expect to be returned.
And so typically, though, when we're using methods, particularly when it's things like click
handles and click handlers and that kind of stuff, you're typically not actually returning anything.
That's not really your goal. And in that case, you'll notice that when I hover over ad restaurant,
it automatically declares a return type of void. Basically, nothing is being returned. That's all that
means. And so there's, you don't need to be explicit about that. Unless, the only time I think this is
really useful is if you want to make sure that no one returns anything, like, if there's a strict
reason why you don't want people to return things, you can certainly jot that down. But otherwise,
what is very much an optional thing? However, though, this is where, once again, we can see something
that we often deal with when it comes to code, which is how many of us, when we're working with
JavaScript events, we have a payload that we pass. And it's like, well, what kind of payload do I
expect? This is not very helpful. So you can always sit here and you can like, I'm sure many of
us have done this, really. Oh, payload is going to be like, done this way for more. But we have
TypeScript to help us out. Again, we just need to help out a little bit. And so how do we define
types for our parameters? Well, it's actually just the colon and then the type that we expect.
So if we do that for both of these, you'll see now that it actually started doing some type
checking. So that if we said like payload dot random message, you'll see that it's like, hey,
whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, wait a second. Random message does not exist on this payload. Like,
this structure does not exist. And so again, another reason why, like, just just a little bit of
TypeScript can make a huge difference in the long running, especially when we all know that like
whether it's yourself that's maintaining the code base, we often forget what we set out to
and where else with this, even if you come back to this code a month later, it will yell at you.
You won't like dive into a rabbit hole and then forget that. At some point, you set a type
something like you intended it to be the shape and then you decided to name it something else. You don't
go worry about that anymore. Otherwise, let's see, hide form here. There's nothing we're doing here,
besides basically taking the show uniform reactive and turning it false. So there's nothing to
type there. And then actually, this here is a typo. So let me just fix this real quick.
There's nothing happening in here. Okay. So that's basically the core functionality of what
most people are using options API for, right? You have your props. You have your data. You have your
methods and you have your computer. So now that I've kind of thrown that information out, do
people have any questions about what I went through or should I dive in any deeper? Yeah.
There's a question about, um, so like you talk about how the word processor is giving you these
what kind of, what kind of the errors like these type errors cause like a build time error or
they run time or if I didn't have the editor telling me what was wrong. Yeah. So let's test that out.
So just to reiterate, so the question here is around what the error provides in addition to just
like the right squiggly line. So let's go ahead and again, let's see this random message here and
save this. And so you'll see now, if I run and pin run builds, oops, I'm in the wrong folder,
N, pin run build. Yes. Okay. Sometimes things don't work when you want them to, but it did this time.
You'll see that it actually stops the build. Now to be clear, something actually, for people
new to TypeScript, it doesn't do runtime compilation, um, if I'm not mistaken. So in other words,
once you've shipped this, it's not going to like retain the types and then check everything to
make sure everything's fine. This is really for while you're developing. Um, this might,
that might change in the future. That's like my big caveat. Maybe browsers will install away
for it to be, um, brought on and stuff. But as of this moment, it's really meant for during
development, and then when you build it to help block these kind of things, and then,
basically, you're on your own after that. So this is where, um, things like checking for your
types is still important. So type guards, so you know sometimes in functions, you'll be like,
if this isn't already do this, if this is a string, do this, you'll still be doing that with
TypeScript. You still, it won't protect you from having to write that code, but what it will do is
protect you from, like, common mistakes like this, where like, oh, at one point you call that,
I, uh, like, for example, uh, restaurants, I call it name at one point, but at one point I call that title,
too, um, when I was building this. And so I was like, oh, wait, oh, that's right. Now I've, and so
that's, if we rely on our brains to remember things, something we just get stumbled a little bit.
And so it's a nice little reminder that, hey, it doesn't exist. Instead, you know, if I can just check
real quick, oh, that's right. I named it, uh, name and set. Do we need to add types to the argument
inside the filter function? The question here is regarding this parameter right here.
So the short answer is, you don't have to do any of this. And I think that it's something I
do want to underscore for a lot of this workshop is that it's really based on the, like,
based on how your team works, right? Because one of the things that I think that made
title difficult to adapt, especially earlier on when people were telling everyone to go all in,
is that people felt like they had to type everything. And then all of a sudden things were colliding
people's knowledge didn't quite match up to what they wanted to do. So then people were slapping
any on everything. And so if you don't know, any is basically like a cheat code for, for
TypeScript to shut up, that's basically what it means. It's just like, stop yelling at me, just like,
ignore it. And at that point, it's basically useless. And so that's why to me, like, for this kind of thing,
if I'm looking at this computer property, honestly, I care most about what's being returned.
In the event that I do think the filter is going to have problems, and like, maybe someone might
not understand the code. That might be something where I can come in here and just say, okay,
you know, just for like documentation, we're going to make sure people know that the parameters
should be of type restaurant. But because filter is a built-in array method, this is not something
I customize, for example. This is like straight up ES6 syntax. We do know that it basically will
iterate through whatever restaurant list is. And so that's basically, it's basically a
choose your own adventure, kind of it. But in this particular case, I might omit it in this case,
because I think the key thing is what you're working with after everything's been returned. But again,
no right or wrong answer. But you could, that's a cool part of what you could say. Exactly, right?
And that's kind of what I want to keep re-emphasizing with this is that if you're like, I feel
a little bit more comfortable. In fact, we'll just leave it in here. There you go. You've annotated it,
people know what to expect. That's all there is to it. Because, and then just to re-emphasize,
like to reinforce this, you'll see that the restaurant without any type definition does inherit,
like, TypeScript does some of that work for you. It's not like it's just like, oh yeah, I got some
array thing. It does know that restaurant list contains this kind of shape. So it does basically
assume that for every item I'm iterating through, it's probably inheriting the shape.
And guaranteed, there may be reasons why this might change, which is why, as mentioned,
if you want to, we can always augment it as needed. So how did it know that restaurant was a type
restaurant without? Yeah. So the reason is because, remember we did that defined component to tell,
like, TypeScript how to find things? If we scroll back up to the data, this is where the data
shape told it that, like, when you do this dot something, oh, restaurant list is of type restaurant.
And so this is kind of some of the dance that has to happen with TypeScript and options API
because of this, this keyword. Because if you hover over this, it's basically useless. But,
actually, it's funny though. You can see here that the create component public instance does
have this filtered restaurant list with the return on here and then can I actually navigate any more?
But anyhow, so that's how it's, it's knowing through all the, all that jumping.